[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
welcome to the stoa we have about 50
rsvp today but i heard there's some zoom
problems so
maybe people will be trickling a little
bit later so
i imagine most people uh know why we're
here
and who john robb is but in in case
there's some new faces uh john rob is an
entrepreneur
author military analyst and worked in
the area of counterterrorism
with the united states special
operations command and he runs a very
popular the global guerrillas report on
patreon
uh where he talks about things like
network tribalism
and uh this is a part of the the stowa's
sense maker in residence series as a
four-part series this is session number
three
and the overall theme is the future so
how uh today's gonna work john's gonna
share his thoughts
uh and if you have any questions just
start throwing them in the chat box uh
right now
uh and then when it comes to the q a
portion i will call on you unmute
yourself
this will eventually go on youtube so if
you don't want your face on youtube just
indicate
uh um that and i'll read it on your
behalf
and the the recorded segment is thirty
uh
60 minutes and then after that we're
going to have like a 30 minute sense
making session
uh split up to break up groups whoever
wants to
stick around so that being said i will
allow jon to unmute himself and then
take you in
[Music]
morning peter um hi everybody thanks for
coming
um what i'd like to do is uh
talk about the future where network
tribalism is taking us
uh just to kind of recap some of the
stuff that we
went over previous sessions um
general idea is that we're being rewired
by social networking
barry mcclellan ask in that regard um
it's changing the way we think we're
moving from
solitary thinkers who read and reflect
and then discuss and debate
to pattern matching people who pattern
match constantly in order to handle the
kind of
deluge of information that we get on an
ongoing basis we basically
sign up for a pattern pattern behavior
or thinking
and we find examples of that
through our scan of of all this
information that's coming through
and when we find an example we kind of
fit it into the
the slot the appropriate slot in the
patterns that we're
curating um that uh
pattern matching is amplified through
something called i call
an empathic trigger because empathy
isn't really
what we think it is
[Music]
in the common thinking is that it's
actually a mental modeling
of of somebody who's a target of an
attack or
somebody who's uh sharing a story and
when you mentally model you take in a
huge amount of information uh in a very
short period of time
by you know your facial expressions
change
to mimic theirs your your muscles tense
uh even the information that you don't
get you fill in yourself
so you get the structure of the model of
what they have inside their mind at that
moment
and then you fill in the rest so it's a
very rapid
information transfer it's very
pre-verbal
early tribalism um that empathic
connection is
one of the basis of of tribe tribe
formation
because you gain a connection with other
people in your tribe through
storytelling
uh and that the people outside that
tribe
are unworthy of empathic connection
uh they're the enemies they're the
they're the foes
uh we see that that mode of thinking has
been
diminishing over time uh replaced by a
literary rational
train of thought uh an approach to you
know how we
handle information but social networking
has
brought it back to the fore and uh
social networking is really great at
empathic communication
and we see examples of that triggers
being used to
uh that spread virally throughout the
throughout the network like uh
the george floyd video uh fits into a
pattern of systemic racism
in the case of the uh oh
the the uh post office most recently
so you have some pictures of post office
boxes being removed which is
you know apparently a standard operating
procedure at the post office
but that was enough to actually prove a
pattern of you know fascist behavior on
trump's side
um and it fit into the pattern and it
spread is empathic we're being
you know cheated we're being uh
oppressed
by this you know this fascist government
so
patterns like that um you have patterns
you have empathic triggering
it creates tribes and we've seen tribes
form across the uh the internet
uh particularly in you know the us
and these tribes are now
growing very quickly and they're posing
a threat to our future so i'll go
through it you know
my thinking in terms of where this is
going in terms of a dark future
we can talk about alternatives later
probably more in the q a
um i in my last report i talked about
tribal totalitarian
totalitarianism um that tribalization
uh being a kind of a network consensus
function
uh is potentially uh
a mechanism for creating a totalitarian
system
what happens is that the um
they draw tribes when they
attempt to assume governance uh draw on
something that
uh comes out of uh fascist thinking and
in germany it was called the gleich
scholten
it's a uh in phase thinking there's a
series of laws
after uh hitler took power to get
the entire country into alignment in
phase
and it took over the media took over
every single hobby group they took over
the civil service and
and everyone had to think the right way
and anyone who
didn't was pushed off or pushed out
that all the political parties uh jews
and others were
pushed out of all of these positions and
and everyone aligned in order to get
ahead
see fascism isn't really what most
people think about
when they hear the word fascists not
jack boots and it's not you know
militarism in the in the in the standard
sense i mean you get that in communism
too with this kind of you know
authoritarian secret secret police what
really makes
fascism unique as a system is that it
solves the problem how do you get a
capitalist economy
to act like a command economy
communism solved that by putting
everything under the same bureaucracy
fascism solved that by putting
uh using glike shelton in phase to get
every single organization pointed in the
same direction
and they kept the capitalist under
underpinnings
in the democratic capitalism we just
incentivized it
so he held out a big bag of money and
everyone ran toward it so it's three
different systems
that like shelton is the basis of what
we're seeing with network tribalism
network tribalism has these vast
patterns that they're uh
curating and that they're growing and
they're uh
moving forward on a daily basis and what
they're doing is they're going through
company by company organization by
organization
and forcing alignment and we saw that
recently in the conflict between the
hong kong protesters and the chinese
government both were seeking alignment
uh over the businesses in hong kong they
would go down the street
and the protesters when they went down
the street they would target the the
companies the larger multinationals that
were aligned with the chinese government
and deface them and then they would skip
over the local ones that were
in favor of the protests and we see that
uh in chinese
efforts to get all of the nba players
and all the companies that do business
in china to
align their what they say about china
with what the communist party would want
them to say
um in the u.s context we're seeing
companies
uh line themselves up in terms of hiring
practices
in terms of how they advertise and
market themselves
in terms of who they support you see all
these signs
for the anti-racist tribe that you know
the beyond signs
uh we see these efforts on the big
platform side to
to push for censorship see alignment
is a modern internet version of that
glass shelter
and it could be on the the left and the
right so far most of the development on
tribal structures have been on the left
mainly in response to the existential
threat that
trump is and and the republicans that
appear to pose
um they see that as an existential
threat and that's caused the tribes to
form
and grow very rapidly so we have a
variety of different tribes we have the
anti-racist anti-fascists being the
largest they have
patterns that they oppose
and unlike tribes in the past tribes are
not tribes in the past were formed based
on
positive messages messages stories that
said this is why we're better together
this is here are the you know the the
adversities that we have gone through
together
uh here's here's here are the rituals
that we
follow in order to tribe members
in the online context since no one can
agree on exactly what everyone is for
since all values are you know tend to be
a subject
or increasingly high percentage of
values are subjectively derived
the values vary by individual
so there's no agreement on exactly what
you are for
there is agreement on what they're
against and these patterns represent
an opposition things to oppose so
racism is this sprawling pattern
you know uh ever increasing nuance and
and and uh depth uh
to oppose and that everyone can agree on
that
or everyone in the tribe can agree on
that and then in the same case of
fascism here are
all the things that we oppose
that are uh demonstrate fascist and they
use
empathic triggers of police beatings and
the like to
to demonstrate to as as visceral
examples of
why why this pattern is is cogent and
real
and uh a threat um or you see it in q
and on i mean q anon is a
pattern matching tribe uh it does the
same
thing but it's targeted against deletes
and the pattern is is is all over the
place but
nonetheless it's something that people
are
using to identify people they oppose
all right um the problem
the problem going forward is that
network alignment
is it can reach a tipping point where
everyone is coerced into alignment you
get this
point where company after company after
company after organization after
organization
aligns and they pledge not to do
business that with with companies and
individuals who don't align
is that the system knocks over and it
goes through a complete
alignment that any viewpoint any network
any
organization that does not align with
those dominant tribal
patterns is eradicated it's not given
any platform it's not
it's not allowed to exist uh
i mean everything touches networks now
and so that means that
uh everything we do in modern society
will be affected by this
so you can't go on a dating app unless
you align you can't go
uh online and talk on facebook either
public or in private chat because the
private chat's being
modern uh and it will be pulled
if you cross the line and that will be
done with increasing sophistication as
they look for
more and more reasons to censor your
your speech
um organizations won't be able to do
business you won't be able to
raise capital you won't be able to
accrue customers
without aligning it
will affect everything you won't be able
to held a job you won't be able to even
maybe even go down the street
if there is facial recognition and
tribes that will actually enforce that
if you go into a restaurant and you're
unknown
person who doesn't comply
so far most of the development of course
has been on the left
in opposition to trump but if the
election goes against trump as it
looks like right now uh what will happen
is
and this is a scenario i'm running out
is a is that
the existential threat from the tribes
on the left will cause
tribe formation on the right to go into
overdrive
and those tribes will grow very quickly
and those will focus
on what they see as anti-american
behavior
a set of behaviors that they see as a
threat
anti-terrorist behavior any kind of
protest any kind of
uh activity that falls outside of of
what they consider norms will be
targeted
and if the tribe goes toward or if the
election goes towards biden there'll
also be
you know the the tribes on the left
won't stay static they will continue to
grow
um they'll continue to protest to try to
take more and more and more
uh power from
what they see is a relatively
ineffectual centrist government
so um
there are a couple you know endgame
scenarios that run
you know that kind of shut this down and
turn it into what i call the long night
is when this tribal pattern or set of
tribal patterns
lock everything all thought all
a discussion of public and private life
into a you know stagnant kind of
orthodoxy
um the
three things that we have to watch out
for is one is that
uh these patterns get locked into aai
and and the biggest ai's we have right
now are social ais they touch three and
a half
four billion people a day in the case of
facebook
um all the big social ais are growing
very quickly they have the data
and the data it determines the quality
of the ai and the quality of the
development um
these ais once given a goal
will increasingly become
becoming increasingly sophisticated at
forcing people
to comply with the orthodoxy that
they've been get handed
um that is a kind of a technological
lock-in
that locks us into us a single
kind of technological artifact that we
can't get out of because it will touch
and reach in to almost everything that
we that we do because
ai as it becomes increasingly like a
utility will be put into every single
product
absolutely every single product and the
quality of your experience at least on a
consumer perspective
is the amount of data you give the
better the the experience with
everything
but that's where these
ais also enter in terms of monitoring
and
defining your future behavior um
another lock-in is a thing to watch out
for
is kind of an economic disaster
where we have a shrinking pie economic
pie
and uh we already see that now with the
the covid recession it's getting worse
it it's really just about to go boom
because
all of the unemployment
uh accelerants and a lot of the
stimulants
that that were coming from the
government have have not passed they're
not going through
and there's going to be a big crunch
this fall
a shrinking pie means that you know
everyone in these in these competing
tribes will be competing for the scarce
amount of
economic resources that are available
they'll be competing for the jobs for
the uh
government programs and the money that's
given them
um they'll be competing for space in the
social space in order to
you know push their set of demands
so you know economic disaster will
accelerate things just as it did in
germany in the late 20s
um and the third thing is that if you
see
counterterrorism forces being used so we
you know the us
had has built this massive
infrastructure for counterterrorism that
encounter insurgency that's used
globally and it can it chews everything
up
that it's targeted and
a lot of the mechanisms necessary to
actually you know legal mechanisms
necessary for
turning it internally to focus it in on
the united states
um were put in place with the patriot
act and follow-on
follow-ons um it's really just a
question of turning the key to
to turn it on and so far we've
stayed away from turning this massive
counter-terrorism machine inward
and that includes everything from the
the monitoring of internal conversations
uh
and discourse uh by the nsa all the way
down to
you know kind of the rapid fire no knock
rates that
that counter insurgency forces would
make and then the kind of internal get
get mo you know secret prison take
people who are
dean terrorism and pop them out
um if that gets turned on
uh say anti-fascists or they get turns
on
uh any of the right-wing groups
that's a lock-in sign because that thing
once it gets going it
has economic and financial reward loops
that lock it in
becomes a multi-billion dollar business
worth you know hundreds of billions of
dollars to the companies and and
and to the organizations that are that
are participating in it
in the case of the right wing group
second piece if you if you widen the net
anyone who says certain things would be
considered a sympathizer
all of that information would then be
available if you've ever said anything
that would
be considered part of the targeted
behaviors
you would be subject to
all sorts of uh government restrictions
on on
what you can do um this isn't restricted
only on the you know only to the tribes
on the right but it could be uh
you know as we just saw uh recently as
tribes on the left as well
it's once it gets going it's a beast
and it will help accelerate moving
towards a long night scenario
um and i don't see the election as as
as the end point on this
is just more of a milestone in this
larger tribal conflict
reliable larger effort to get everyone
in the country
and to align and then expanding
potentially that globally
um it's a pretty dark scenario
but you know every day seems to prove it
more and more correct
so um now i just kind of set this up
you can open it up for questions
cool so we got a few questions in the
chat
joseph if you can unmute yourself and
ask your question
sure uh can you hear me all right yep
so the the question is there appears to
be on the right
a tribe developing around the concept of
disconnection
leaving cities self-reliance not being
active on social networking
uh so i have two follow-on questions to
that
one is could a tribe actually be built
around the concept of disconnection
uh when the when the fight is over who
is connected to the network
uh and secondarily um would a
disconnected tribe be
seen as a threat by the opposing tribe
because they can't be reached and
monitored or would they just be seen as
a non-threat because they have
essentially canceled themselves yeah
i've seen a tri i've seen a big effort
recently
um you know center right people from
california
that i know wealthier
more likely to do it of you know going
mobile
selling their stuff and starting to try
to find a place to kind of wait this out
and those people tend to think you know
far future like like a jordan hall for
instance right
i mean he thinks about the far future he
sees this coming
may not be able to describe it in the
same way i do but he feels a threat and
we're seeing people trying to go mobile
in order to avoid being crunched
so you know i went through this uh
thinking back
whoa uh back in you know 2008
with the resilient communities and and
the stuff i was doing
back then um and what i found in you
know looking at
uh you know different
historical situations is that um
you know people who are disconnected
people who are uh
thinking that they're gonna stay out of
it tend to become targets
uh you know they're not part
of the the larger conflict uh they're
just seen as a kind of a source of
resources
that big can be acquired um
it's not some this this kind of conflict
is not a not the kind of thing that will
leave any place untouched
uh it's also um
you know from the government from the
counter surgency side you know
disconnection you know going silent uh
is kind of a sign of being a potential
threat
so it raises your visibility um i've
tended
given the stuff i write about in
counterinsurgency and
guerrilla warfare and the like i tend to
put everything out
i put my name i put my name on my blog
back in 2002
and i put my thoughts out there
in the public so that serves as kind of
a
kind of a signaling effort to show that
i'm not a threat to any kind of
future counter insurgency effort um
can you wait it out uh
resilient communities fantastic you know
in terms of uh surviving any kind of
infrastructure disconnection or
infrastructure breakdown
we're going to see a lot of that um
harder to see it surviving a uh
socio-political collapse in that regard
you know you really want to be with a
larger group
and uh the protections it affords and as
honorous as that may be that may be the
dominant system
you know survival strategy
yeah do you ever hear about uh bruce
sterling my friend bruce sterling had a
pretty cool little thing that he put out
once he said uh
in the apocalypse it wasn't the you know
small groups of people who were you know
well armed that survived it it was like
the big mega churches
right i mean they had manpower and and
weaponry galore
and they were able to exert control over
areas that
you couldn't see happening on the small
screen just rolled over the smaller
groups
and that's your question
uh yes it did thank you
so i have a follow-up question on that
um uh joseph's question
a gesture towards like the long term and
i was wondering some short term to
medium term strategies
to deal with memetic extortion in order
for these tribes to create
that alignment um and i'm curious if you
can speak on sort of like
these technique extortion techniques
that are currently happening amongst his
tribes
and how can we gain kind of like
sovereignty to protect ourselves from it
just maybe just enough to buy some time
in order for like this to think about
more long-term solutions
oh wow um
try to avoid alignment i mean most
companies
you know even the even the street even
the uh the small shops on the streets
that are suffering protests
uh they flipped so they put you know up
support for the protest even even though
that they were being you know looted or
burned or whatever it's just
it didn't matter they they align out of
self-preservation
and you see that with big companies and
and their quick
move to alignment um the cost of
alignment will be different
you know right now i mean the tribe's on
the left 10 towards
kind of moral warfare so uh
you are shaming and disconnection
from the group of uh morally aligned and
you know around
their center of gravity uh will hurt
your business
you just get fewer customers and you you
get
an inability to buy from certain places
and and
supply chains breakdown on the right the
tribes will probably be
focused on disruption so uh you'll
immediately be disrupted
whether that's a there's a variety of
different ways to do that there's from
the troll side
we saw trump do that the other day with
the goodyear
um by uh calling for a boycott and it
even though they may not materialize and
as as effectively as you may see on the
left but that disruption can be
just easily done it drove down their
stock price and it probably will shave
off five to ten percent of their
earnings
this year so um
disruption can go into the physical
realm meaning breaking down the
electricity system that supplies their
factories breaking down their uh supply
chains
making it impossible for them to operate
um so there's cost that is
to non-alignment um
potentially if you if you i mean you
could get out of this by
going overseas and aligning landing
internationally
uh but i don't know if that's actually
going to provide you much
much of a breathing room much breathing
room over the longer term because
china's expanding its network
you know its consensus network and the
whoever wins the battle in the us will
expand its
and uh we'll see countries that
start to align after after a certain
period of time
so i don't know where you could actually
go to maybe avoid this completely
cool um okay next question
bill you had a question
hi yeah can you hear me okay yep
uh two questions actually if you don't
mind they're kind of related
um one was um you've made several
comments about tribalism being a
function of the left
while at this current moment in time at
least um
but what's your perspective on the
republican senate's consistent support
of trump against their own
internal beliefs like there's many
republicans very clearly
anti-trump but toeing the line um
because of
out of the same self preservation that
you're talking about
um you know being part of the tribe kind
of speak
and then the other thing um you also
mentioned that you didn't
you weren't sure how much difference the
election is going to make
so on that idea do you see it possible
that a different leader
some magical leader could could be able
to
bridge the current left-right uh tribal
structure in the u.s okay
well um uh the senators
in the republican party aligned with
trump uh because
they would be hounded out of office if
they did trump has
within the republican party and at least
the last three and a half years
he was more popular than reagan so
there's a reason why he's still at 41
when
people who back him and put him in
office
they wouldn't accept any senator going
against them
in the next election they would be out
and in the meantime they would be
hounded
constantly by by trolls and people
inside their
uh inside their state
so um
and there's also kind of a faustian kind
of element there they get a lot
of what they want out of it out of the
relationship meaning judicial alignment
and other things
and all they have to do is kind of uh
prostitute themselves a little bit but i
mean that's politics and
you know that's not far from you know
what we see in most political behavior
now do we see any kind of magical leader
i don't see a political leader uh
emerging that could bridge the gap
um i mean the best the democrats have
been able to put up
is a somebody who's running on a on
a zero platform i mean the only platform
that biden is running on is that he's
not trump
his his ideas hold no kind of sway and
no kind of appeal
um you know it's tough tough to see
anyone
being even you know generated by the
system that we have right now
uh and uh i don't see the u.s political
system as being
effective enough and legitimate enough
at this juncture to
to uh suspect that we will see a
political leader
with the capability of bridging the
divide i mean
a big reason why we're seeing network
tribalism rise
is that the current political system has
become
very ineffectual it's not working it's
not generating good decisions
uh it's not delivering the political
goods it should
um
so i i suspect the the solution won't
come out of the existing system
i mean establishment seems to think that
returning back to
turning back the clock to obama years
may may solve everything i don't think
it's going to solve anything
to help
do you have a yeah very very
disappointing but uh
but in the in the long run but thank you
you have a follow-up question billy said
he had two
oh he had two in that yeah okay
cool uh aaron uh you had a question
sure so uh first i've been following
your work for a long time thanks john
i really enjoy it uh
two is there a certain scale size
capitalization that might confer
immunity or buffer
effect because like the big institution
that mega church point is very
interesting
um and i know that a lot of smaller
organizations
tend to not have group cohesion in the
sense that they might be inclined to say
more drastic or dramatic things create a
targeting effect around themselves and
then
somebody kind of marks them but bigger
organizations have these
kind of need political needs so to say
to navigate a lot of different views at
the same time and create some kind of
consensus which the empathic triggering
kind of
societally does not do so that's kind of
i think just that's my question and then
the second thing is
if that is a possibility is how how
would somebody navigate that middle
in a time where of wide scale
polarization
right um
so i'm reading it as a consensus
positive view
you know who you know which which
organizations
can generate a large degree of positive
cohesion
with a positive message and that's
extremely hard to do in this environment
everything is built to take things down
to reduce it
to you know cleave it break it down um
wow the only the only kind of
organization that seems to have
worked is um in putin's russia with the
cross holdings of of of corrupt
companies so
he is reportedly the wealthiest man in
the world over 200 billion dollars
he has all those cross ownership
ties to all the major companies
so they're offered they're kind of
legally bound to each other
and and connected and they tend to be
like the biggest
lump of cohesion within russia and
everything else is kept in a chaos
which is one of the potential end points
here is that that
that is the uh you know
the only thing that's cohesive is this
corrupt core and then everything else is
just
pulsed and disrupted in a way that keeps
it constantly
in chaos constantly everyone's at each
other's throats
um no meaningful opposition can form
opposition groups are funded um to fight
other opposition groups uh if the leader
gets
too pesky they're poisoned or taken out
uh
and um that's the only thing i see is
you know at least in within the
environments that we're we're
moving into um that have proven that
they're actually
uh viable in the sense that they didn't
have a complete
point yeah coalition um
coalitions are hard to form it that
financial ties are interesting
and maybe that can be uh repurposed into
a uh
kind of a a positive cohesive core that
has
financial cross holdings and um
even though they don't agree they
represent
large blocks of agreement and can form a
basis for
getting things done in a positive way
okay
thank you yep
all right uh laszlo you had a question
yeah i think it actually uh calls up
well with dbs one x's
my version of the question is there a
way who's tribalism
too for a positive effect like
resilience or not uh because like i'm
glad to be difficult
maybe but it didn't seem to
[Music]
um okay so
you know i'm in favor of small-scale
tribalism in terms of cohesion
and what it can do in terms of building
resilience and and
making you more effective at the local
level but the only thing that seems to
have
only part of tribalism that seems to
have uh
gone on on a
meta scale is this anti-tribalism and so
it's a
set of behaviors it's a pattern of
behaviors that that
people can oppose and it's kind of a
variant of the open source ideas that
people can agree on this
but they can't agree about what they're
for now
is it possible that uh we can
we could build a tribe around a
set of things that we oppose that are
narrowly constrained
right um that are uh
narrow enough that we that they don't
pose a threat
okay and that they're applied in a way
that isn't isn't too heavy-handed
yes that's possible um and that uh
the problem right now is that the the
patterns that are
being developed or metastasizing they're
growing in every which way they're being
curated by millions of people in their
open source and so
everything is being uh added to them and
then you have these empathic triggers
that turn it into a
you know tribal framework meaning that
uh
everyone who's you know affected by this
pattern they're
given complete empathic connection and
and they're
part of your tribe and you feel deeply
they are you
and that everyone who is doing everyone
is potentially uh
identified by this pattern is a
tribal enemy i mean they are afforded no
empathy connection and
and they are
sub-human in many respects so um
can we constrain it that was kind of my
hope is that we'd never get to the
tribalism point
that we would have you know a consensus
form
around a uh very narrow set
of ideas and then we get those done
and that we use dissent to kind of break
it apart kind of a new dynamic in
in uh network decision making is you
know
at the social level is that we'd have
the
one side would be complete consensus and
the other side would be chaos and those
would be the
new left and right and
the middle ground would be this
consensus that would form around
something that was timely that was
necessary that that had to get done and
that we couldn't get agreement on any
other way
because the other system the other
decision making systems were ineffective
in this environment and that the dissent
would break that down
when that consensus failed to
achieve its goal or or didn't uh provide
any
further benefits it was overreaching so
um
yeah the is it possible that we form a
tribe around
a narrow set yeah i mean that would give
it a lock-in
but you know tribalism tends to be a
disorganized thing it can get way out of
hand and in the current
incarnation uh
very dangerous
sorry okay yeah goodness the same gloomy
but that answers my question
all right ryan just threw a question in
the chat ryan if you can ask your
question
ryan i'm gonna ask you to unmute
yourself there you go
there we go sorry about that um so i was
just wondering
do we do you expect that there to be any
any technological innovation supporting
uh the tribalization or do you think
most of the technological innovations
already taken place
and that most of it's going to be social
innovation from here on out
that's going to yeah
there's a lot of technological
innovation
biggest of which is where ai goes and um
i mean mcluhan offhandedly said that you
know the way we survived this
kind of global village villager future
where everyone's at each other's throats
um and in each other's business
is that we turn society into detect into
a technological artifact
and that doesn't kind of mitigate these
connections to kind of give us some
personal space because we're so
close to each other i mean when somebody
tweets something online
it's like in your face it's like in your
pocket
and then you took it out and it's like
there um that's
closeness is isn't seen anywhere else
in terms of tribalization the ais that
are
aligned will accelerate the whole effort
and that it will do it down to the
personal level there's only way that you
actually can
can manipulate or censor people down to
the conversational level
uh build profiles on them and and
manipulate every aspect of their
digital identity on an ongoing basis on
a real-time basis is through ai
to do it for 330 million people here or
do it for three and a half billion
people it can be done through a uh
in real time and as we get more and more
interconnected as we start to add ar to
things where our
visual and auditory environment is
completely manipulatable um
yeah things get really dicey uh
and if tribal alignment is being forced
upon everybody um
yeah that's that's how it's going to
actually manifest itself through those
technological developments that answer
it
it does so uh it sounds like you would
say that uh
you see ai is the primary driver and
then
maybe some supported technologies like
ar or vr
yeah i mean you know i don't see ai as a
kind of a human-like
i mean despite all this effort to try to
create human-like intelligence i
see it more of a symbiote uh
i mean symbiotic with us it's it lives
in the spaces between us
and those of the ais that are taking off
becoming the biggest
those are the neural nets or becoming
the richest and more
most nuanced um that social space that
that space between us is is uh
full of data and um it's very easy to
manipulate because
particularly since we're becoming kind
of digital entities
uh things that you know
one way out of this potentially and that
comes out of this kind of
view of ai is that uh we start to
get more control over our digital
identities
uh i propose kind of kind of data
ownership is that you own
all of the data that you that's produced
on you and collected about you
every manifestation of it everything
that's built on that
um you have an ownership stake in and
that
that controlling interest drives a
serious development
could create a dynamic where
we see the development of beneficial ais
that maximize your achievement
the achievement of your digital identity
and every improvement in that digital
identity confirms benefits to you
that may be a kind of a marketplace kind
of dynamic to get us out of this
networking dynamic that could counter
this
but i don't see anyone even moving
towards that they're they're still
debating
you know what privacy is uh kind of a
never-ending debate
rather than moving towards something
that's more definable more tangible like
ownership
okay thanks john yep thanks
um yeah you know i have actually a
follow-up on that one um
sure uh
i like this this young chauhan he's this
korean german philosopher
uh he says like the internet pornifies
our life
right even our political views and you
know how what you you mentioned like
good offenses make good neighbors type
of thing but
um if we know everything about everyone
then you know there's like that
i think that's like psychological term
uh dissimilarity cascades
the more we know about someone we
actually dislike them more um
and so i was wondering if you could
speak on the kind of like the addictive
like kind of spectacle aspects of the
current social media landscape like
twitter facebook
and maybe how like that tristan harris
humane tech movement
might ameliorate some of that if it
picks up
well i mean this is the global villagers
effect right so um
we're all put in close proximity to each
other
we're uh cheap cheek to jowl uh
all of our thoughts are lying side by
side with the thoughts of other people
and you know anytime we see something
that's
dissonant anything that's potentially
objectionable because of the proximity
to us and we we react strongly we you
know
we regenerate it generates outrage it
hits us harder
and that proximity is not going away i
mean unless it's kind of
kind of injected into the system and
what all the benefits of the system is
that we
we were packed in
to the system together as close as we
are
um but there's ways to potentially uh
fix that and that's that technological
artifact idea is that you know
can there be ways of just softening
that interconnection kenny can be
greased uh
can can group formation and interaction
be
easier and
you know kind of reducing that that
friction
but you know what we've seen so far from
the ais from the big social networks is
um you know they're focusing on you know
stickiness factors and
you know maximizing the time that people
spend online and
you know they emphasize the uh
the period the things that really you
know get people
engaged and that that tends towards the
more outrageous so we see that on
youtube we saw that in facebook
and um so they've amplified that
that outrage um
is there any way out of it think of it
maybe how do you
how do you uh ameliorate it within the
context of a village
well you create other villages
decentralize um
[Music]
i don't know of any other way other than
a technological kind of intervention
kind of a softening from that ai that
lives in the space between us
maybe more limited connection
we disconnect more but that you know
everything's working against that when
ar hits
it's just about here i mean everything
in your visual and auditory environment
will be
modified and that will become so
addicting it's
it it's crazy because i mean living
without that
would be like like turning off the
internet completely
or worse it's like turning off all
electronics
including you know electricity and
lights just like the lessening
would be bland it'd be like going from
like the matrix turning it off and going
into that life of
living underground it's just that
extreme
that answer it or not you want to you
have a
way to point me in a better direction
don't
uh but i do have uh an interesting
question to end us off with but i want
to
ask kyle's question first
and kyle wants me to read this on his
behalf okay is there a chance that
nationalism will be harnessed as an
identity as it has been in the past
because it sure seems like that to to my
writings on the medic tribe
um that the entropy is still increasing
yet we also expect some uh um
sorry does nationalism align with these
ideas because they control ai thanks
okay so nationalism um where i see it on
the
uh coming out of the right is uh and
even
there is a little bit of the center left
is trying to you know form a tribe
around this
mostly bureaucrats associated with the
national security system or center left
they're pushing for a what they call it
something anti-americanism as defined by
these
behaviors it's not like a positive
nationalism it is an
anti-american or anti-anti-national
behavior
you know what constitutes that well if
you do this
you're anti-american uh
so a lot of the stuff that pushed back
on trump with russia and the like is in
that anti-national
side we're going to see that rise up on
the on the right
in terms of you know behaviors
associated with that
biden and and harris will be exhibiting
so um
it's gonna be uh more an anti-feature
than a positive pro feature
did i miss a part of that question
should i
uh he says thanks privately yeah
privately to me so i think
i think you got right um i did get an
email question
from shannon day and uh you touched on
it already but i'll read it
because the framing is somewhat
different i might jog some insights
okay so how do you view the relationship
which is often seen as symbiotic between
powerful hierarchy organizations
like amazon and network tribes we
obviously see corporations signaling
some sort of alignment but it does but
does it go deeper than that for example
amazon might ban a couple of books to
appease a seemingly powerful network
tribe
that network tribe might therefore not
be anti-amazon
in short amazon provides the monopoly
that allows them to have
some sway in terms of which books docs
can get banned in return amazon singles
alignment to their tribe
thoughts yeah um network alignment
you know reaches inside these
organizations that remember you know
a lot that alignment's based on that
like shelton is that this
how do you get a capitalist economy to
all point in the same direction
every company every organization every
individual all
moving in the same direction and
what we're seeing with the big companies
is that uh these tribes are reaching
inside the bureaucracy they're flipping
people and those people are internal
watchdogs you see the kind of revolts in
google and you see the revolts in
facebook
and then i'm going to see the revolts in
in the government bureaucracies as well
where people were flipped or part of the
tribe
who have a different you know say in
fourth generation warfare terms are kind
of a different primary loyalty
are are fighting against any kind of
directive from the top
of the hierarchy that they are a part of
um
so the bigger and more
electronic our supply system is our
retail system our system is uh the
easier it is to
force alignment because then
instantly instantiate that across the
entire country
it takes you know if it was a largely
offline environment it take forever to
try to get
things to align um one thing germany
founded with their glad shelton is that
you know it happened much faster than
they ever anticipated
and i think it was through the crucible
of the of the
depression people were aligning out of
self-preservation because to not is to
not have a job and that environment
was yeah so
um but it happened even quick in the in
a relatively disconnected environment so
in a connected environment it can be
sweeping and it could be
almost instantaneous um and uh
since the trip the tribe's pattern is
constantly being curated and
it's metastasizing it will constantly
look for new ways to
to force alignment in the companies and
organizations that
uh purport to be aligned always be
people you know digging in and saying
look look what they did
they didn't align and this is an example
of it and then
they'd be swarmed and then they would
change their behaviors fire that person
change
you know redux the organization in order
to
you know force to get back into
alignment you're going to see that all
the time and it's for nonsense i mean
largely these patterns are
filled with that's a couple key truths
but frankly
you know most of it is really it gets
into
nutty land i mean as we saw with q9 it's
mostly naviland but it's like
it's a pattern that has some elements
that seem true or
appear to be true um within it
and that's enough to keep it all
cohesive
yeah i i don't think hierarchies have
much of a chance i mean what we're
what we're seeing on a meadow scale we
have you know old nationalism
as a kind of the tribal decision-making
system we have
institutions which are the bureaucracies
that run modern life everything from
academia to
science to government to corporations
those are hierarchies great at
mobilizing and then we have
uh markets which are used in elections
so like the
ahead of the of these these
bureaucracies
by and large uh even corporate
bureaucracies are
dictated by the market and then and the
um
the new one is the networks and the
networks appear to be stronger than
everything
and they can enforce their will across
the board right so um
we'll end it with paul's question
hey john um all right so my question is
um
so given that governments at least in
the us are seem so far behind all these
trends
what other levers do you think society
has to uh to change the incentive
structures on platforms that drive
network tribalism
yeah the government's um tended to shy
away from actually trying to force
platforms into a light
because they don't really have anything
they really want to alignment they're so
divided
and so ineffectual and unable to
generate consensus through their own
actions
and these platforms are multinational
there's always a worry on and if every
single
government wanted to have their way on
the platform um
no one no one would agree no there's
every every other government would try
to force them
not to change um
so the only system that seems to be
effective at
actually forcing these platforms into
alignment are these travel structures
and they're doing a lot through kind of
internal
subversion they're flipping employees
and getting those employees to align
so far mostly most of the the effort has
been forced on you know
forcing those companies to align with
u.s values within the u.s but the real
gold mine is when it goes overseas
because you have
a huge number of three and a half
billion people on facebook right so
places like the philippines 90 plus of
their news comes from facebook
you know you get countries like that all
across southeast asia
all across africa or in that system
if you can get control of these
platforms you can
dictate a way of thinking across
billions of people
simultaneously particularly with ai
support
so there's a global element here um
it would sneak up and go faster than any
of these individual governments can
can respond um if they uh already see
facebook you know involved in elections
globally sometimes siding with one side
over the other
deleting posts uh
you know in in the mix in terms of
deciding what's true and what's not
in terms of those elections and i don't
think they have nearly the expertise
necessary to do it but nonetheless
they're already involved yeah if you can
control the technological platforms and
basically everything outside of china is
on u.s platforms
um then you can dictate the future of
the world
if you force alignment
it's not going to come from the
government so i don't see them even
being players or
they're too divided and uh every single
disruption we get from the
the complex global environment that
we're in makes them weaker
makes them less effective they just
don't
aren't really good at responding to
those those events
all right so we're gonna end here um
you know i will sneak in my last
question which will take on what uh so
the question was
um are you uh optimistic or pessimistic
about all this um and then then the
question i'll take on to that is what
are we gonna talk about for the final
session uh next week
uh optimistic long-term pessimistic
short-term
um it it feels like this this
the tribal network growth is going so
quickly and alignment is happening so
fast
um that the political establishment is
totally out of
out of touch with what's going on
particularly you know
uh you know the senior political leaders
on the democratic side just
they think they can just turn back the
clock and it's just not going to happen
they're going to get rolled from both
sides
i think though over the long term that
we'll come up with some solution we have
to
there's a outside chance that we'll get
locked in the ai will lock us into these
like orthodoxies
and you know we get that long night
scenario that just can't get out of
we're fighting this opaque machine and
there's opaque
intelligence that's living in between
all of us and it's dictating a way of
interacting with everybody else that we
can't find a mechanism to
get around and it's in everything it's
in the ar it's in
every communication that we have
electronically and that those
electronics are
getting deeper and deeper into our lives
and disconnection
doing it onesies and twosies won't fix
it
and any kind of disruption
at the physical level will have
relatively little effect because of the
the amount of interconnection and then
the amount of dependency we have on the
system
and we're doing it we're going blindly i
mean i mean i'm just a relatively small
voice in this and
i don't see anyone talking about this
stuff mermaid is just not out there and
i'm looking i'm looking for somebody
even who sees it
and i tend to be a little right you know
i tend to hit
hit the themes that actually play out
and i
i see people going in all sorts of
different directions and they're not
they're not seeing the threat here
i'm part of like different groups online
who think about the future
you are too and a lot of other people
here are and
they have all these different scenarios
and all these different mechanisms for
doing it
and i just see these they don't see the
tribalism coming and they don't see that
you know once things are aligned all
those ideas are wiped clean
it's just gone because none of them will
align
with the patterns that are being opposed
they won't be allowed
because they'll either be fascist or
racist or
anti-american or terrorist or you're
going to be
you know whatever it is it's like
won't be there that diversity will be
gone denuded from the landscape it's
that's disheartening uh
i wish it was you know more thinking i
don't see it i don't see a cohesive
mechanism yet that will get us out of
this
maybe the little seed with the private
ownership of the of the data that may be
one of those things that sets in motion
a change
that could be built upon ownership of
that data then
gives you a little bit of space as an
individual
that the like-minded individuals can
start to connect
but without it our data is owned by the
state it's owned by corporations
they can do whatever they want and
define privacy whatever which way they
want
we're lost our digital selves or
the thing that generates uh you know uh
how we connect with the world and
thinking that generates our wealth is
be lost out there in the ether it's
under under the control of other people
that's other systems anyway i'm probably
running a lot for this answer but
so on that note bring your positivity
and optimism next week for
for for john and then the chat box
uh any kind of theme that we're gonna
run with next week
uh well i'll start to maybe put together
some stuff on
uh ways out of us we can build on the
the ownership side we can maybe go into
um kind of
something i haven't fully fleshed out in
the report yet and i was thinking about
doing it was the uh
the selfish ledger bearing on that
uh if you have seen that have you seen
it no
oh okay well worth watching this idea
that well
we can cover that um it's kind of a cool
concept if it's ripped upon in the
correct way cool cool uh so yeah i put
that in the
selfish ledger thing and kind of like
maybe reading material people can look
at
so uh i'll close out with some few
announcements if you want to stick
around for
another 25 minutes for some sense making
please do so
but first john as always thank you for
coming to the stall
sharing your wisdom if you'd like to
get immediate access to this video and
the other videos and john's thoughts you
can uh sign up for his patreon uh you
can also sign up for the stowe's patreon
if you like these scents making a
residence series
and you can check out the stove for
upcoming events we have one tonight at 7
30 p.m with daniel schmuckenberger
talking about
the possibility of a modern stoicism and
uh
next um or this what is it i don't know
why he's taken off he seems to be one of
the guys that's fleeing
oh right so i just was wondering what
you know ask him
put him on the spot with that you know
why are you kind of like
becoming a nomad so like jordan and like
others
i just want to see their thinking
process because they haven't really
articulated that
do you want to come and ask that on your
uh
okay i'll toss that i'll i'll see what i
can do we'll have more gravitas if it
comes directly from you
all right i'm sorry go ahead no no
worries um
so uh august 26th what is that that's a
a wednesday um we have uh we have
two ran uh analysts uh john arquillo
and uh david ronfeld who they released a
monograph called whose story wins the
rise of the noah's fear
noah politik and information age states
craft
they cited a medic try paper too so
there's some kind of overlap with
a lot of the stuff we talked about today
and this is
the first book the emergence of a new
apolo tape so if you like what's
happening right here
in this uh conversation you'll
definitely like that one
uh so you can rsvp to that uh that being
said
thank you for coming out if you want to
hang out uh we'll go for bio break for
one minute and then we'll start the
sense making groups in a moment